Is י"ח חי yud-chet chai 18, we pick up at the bottom
of י"ז עמוד ב yud-zayin amud bet the middle
אמה עברייה amah ivriyah we're dealing now with how a Hebrew slave
goes free and some differences between a male and a female slave.
So אמה עברייה amah ivriyah okay and we also dealt of course
with the מצות הענקה mitzvah hanakah of ladening down with gifts. Okay
and now the two dots about five lines before the lines get
wide, eight lines before the lines get wide. אמה עברייה אינה עובדת
לא את הבן ולא את הבת. amah ivriyah einah ovedet lo et
haben velo et habat. A Hebrew maidservant does not serve the son
or the daughter, meaning we learned that by an עבד עברי eved
ivri if he's not a נרצע nirtza he continues his six years
to the children because it's basically like a six-year contract. If he
is a נרצע nirtza then he only serves the what do you
call it?
If he is a נרצע nirtza then he only serves the son
but not the other heirs. Am I getting that right? One minute.
עבד עברי עובד את הבן ואינו עובד את הבת. eved ivri oved
et haben ve'eino oved et habat. One minute.
No, excuse me, excuse me. One minute. Let me get this straight
again.
Okay.
Right, right. I'm sorry. An עבד עברי eved ivri will do the
six years for the son but not for another heir, that's what
we said at the end of yesterday, he'll do the six years
for the son but not for another heir. A נרצע nirtza doesn't
even do the six doesn't even do anything for for any for
even for the son. A נרצע nirtza goes free when the master
dies and an אמה עברייה amah ivriyah also goes free when the
master dies. Okay, so אמה עברייה אינה עובדת לא את הבן ולא
את הבת. amah ivriyah einah ovedet lo et haben velo et habat.
Yeah, let's just do this again. Okay.
You have
עבד
עברי eved ivri
and
אמה עברייה, amah ivriyah, okay, and here you have the six-year version,
right, and the נרצע. nirtza.
Okay, so those are the two versions. And basically you have בן
ben and other other heirs, other heirs, okay,
which would be בת bat and other heirs. Okay, so an עבד
עברי eved ivri works for the son, a continuation of the father,
not for the other heirs. A נרצע nirtza doesn't work for either,
okay, and we pointed out mostly my read of that is to
emphasize that he's not property, but this is like a six-year contract
so at least the son that's considered a direct continuation, you finish
out the contract, other heirs you do not because, you know, it's
really a contract is between people, it's not something that's about an
inheritance, so you don't finish a contract for some heir, but you
finish a contract for the son that's a continuation of the father.
A נרצע nirtza but interestingly is neither, and an אמה עברייה amah
ivriyah is neither.
Okay, so that's אמה עברייה אינה עובדת לא את הבן ולא את
הבת.
amah ivriyah einah ovedet lo et haben
velo et habat.
It's so weird about the בת bat part. I mean because, you
know, the בת bat would inherit just as much as the בן
ben would if there's no בן ben around.
Right, but she's not considered a continuation, that's just a law in
inheritance, it's not as a continuation.
Okay, מנא הני מילי, mena hanei milei, where's this from? אמר רב
פפא אמר רב אדא בר אהבה, amar rav pappa amar rav adda
bar ahavah, first said, ואף לאמתך תעשה כן. ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken.
Okay, so this is about the פסוק pasuk about הענקה, hanakah, you
know, הענק תעניק לו מצאנך ומגרנך ומיקבך כאשר ברכך ה' אלוהיך תתן
לו ha'anek ta'anik lo mitzonecha umigornecha umiyekvecha ka'asher berachecha hashem elokecha titein
lo and it's ואף לאמתך תעשה כן ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken
is somewhere in there, let me read the פסוקים pesukim inside to
be clear on הענקה. hanakah.
Well, we're going to discuss that in a minute, which is why
I want to read the פסוקים pesukim inside. So the פסוקים pesukim
say, okay, כי ימכר לך אחיך העברי או העברייה ועבדך שש שנים
ובשנה השביעית תשלחנו חפשי מעמך וכי תשלחנו חפשי מעמך לא תשלחנו ריקם
הענק תעניק לו וכולי
ki yimacher lecha achicha ha'ivri o ha'ivriyah va'avadcha
shesh shanim uvashanah hashevi'it teshalchenu chofshi me'imach vechi teshalchenu chofshi me'imach lo
teshalchenu reikam ha'anek ta'anik lo vechulu etc. מגורנך ומיקבך כאשר ברכך וזכרת
כי עבד היית בארץ מצרים ויפדך ה' אלוהיך משם על כן אנכי
מצוך את הדבר הזה. migornecha umiyekvecha ka'asher berachecha vezacharta ki eved hayita
be'eretz mitzrayim vayifdecha hashem elokecha misham al ken anochi metzavecha et hadavar
hazeh. Okay, והיה כי יאמר אליך לא אצא מעמך כי אהבך ואת
ביתך כי טוב לו עמך ולקחת את
המרצע vehayah ki yomar eilecha lo eitzei me'imach ki ahevecha ve'et beitecha
ki tov lo imach velakachta et hamartze'a which you do
the the the piercing the ear ונתת באזנו ובדלת והיה לך עבד
עולם ואף לאמתך תעשה כן. venatata be'ozno uvadelet vehayah lecha eved olam
ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken.
So according to פשט pshat of the פסוקים, pesukim, you can do
the ואף לאמתך תעשה כן ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken doing נרצע. nirtza.
But as we've been assuming until now and as we're going to
say explicitly, a בת, bat, an אמה עברייה amah ivriyah does not
do נרצע nirtza because the whole point of the אמה עברייה amah
ivriyah was to lead to her being married, not for this ongoing
service, servitude. So the גמרא gemara is going to read the ואף
לאמתך תעשה כן ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken about the הענקה, hanakah, about
the ladening down with gifts. Okay, דאמר קרא ואף לאמתך תעשה כן.
de'amar kra ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken. הקישו הכתוב לנרצע. hekisho hakatuv lenirtza.
So but it
but it is dealing the immediate context is with the נרצע, nirtza,
the guy with the hole in the ear. So that's the context,
even though it's not the הלכה halacha that she's not נרצע. nirtza.
מה נרצע אינו עובד לא את הבן ולא את הבת mah nirtza
eino oved lo et haben velo et habat the same way you
said a נרצע nirtza doesn't work for either, okay, אף אמה עברייה
אינה עובדת לא את הבן ולא את הבת af amah ivriyah einah
ovedet lo et haben velo et habat the same by the אמה
עברייה. amah ivriyah. והאי, vehai, the גמרא gemara says, ואף לאמתך תעשה
כן ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken מהאי הקישא? mehai hekeisha? That's what it's
coming to tell me? המיבעי ליה לכדתניא, hamibayei leih lechidetanya, ואף לאמתך
תעשה כן ve'af la'amatcha ta'aseh ken להעניק, leha'anik,
for the ladening down with gifts. אתה אומר להעניק או אינו אלא
לרציעה ata omer leha'anik o eino ela lirtzi'ah maybe it's like פשט
pshat of the פסוקים pesukim it means you do the רציעה rtzi'ah
itself. כשהוא אומר ואם אמר יאמר העבד, keshehu omer ve'im amar yomar
ha'eved, this is in the פסוק pasuk in שמות. shemot. which speaks
about the רציעה *retzia*. If the slave says, so it didn't just
say ואם אמר יאמר *v'im amar yomar*, we know it's talking about
a slave. So the fact that it says העבד *ha'eved*, it's to
tell you ולא *v'lo* אמה עבריה amah Ivriyah, *amah ivriya*, not an
אמה עבריה ama ivriya? *amah ivriya*. So right away רציעה *retzia* you
know that you don't do the רציעה *retzia*. המה אני מקיים *Hamani
mikayem*, so you know based on a דרשה drasha *drasha* from the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in משפטים *Mishpatim*, we take the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
in דברים *Devarim* out of context and we say it's not talking
about רציעה *retzia*. So the only thing left for it to be
talking about is the ladening down with gifts. המה אני מקיים ואף
לאמתך תעשה כן v'af l'amatcha ta'aseh ken *Hamani mikayem v'af l'amascha ta'aseh
chein*, להעניק *l'haanik*. Okay, but now that's one דרשה *drasha* that you
don't do the רציעה *retzia*, you do the הענקה hanaka, *haanaka*, but
then how do we know it means that it's similar to a
נרצע nirtza *nirtza* for this issue that she goes free when the
master dies? Okay, if so, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says how do
you learn both? אם כן *Im kein*, נכתוב קרא לאמתך כן *nichtov
kra l'amascha chein*. Just say ואף לאמתך כן *v'af l'amascha chein*. מאי
תעשה *Mai ta'aseh*, you should do? Since there's an extra word, שמע
מינה תרתי *shma mina tarti*, you deduce two segment of הלכה halacha
*halacha*.
Okay, so somehow, this is the second part.
The second part is that she's not עובדת את הבן ולא את
הבת *ovedes es haben v'lo es habas* just like the נרצע *nirtza*.
I thought so, you don't דרשן סמוכות *darshan smuchas*? What happened to
that?
What do you mean?
It's right next to נרצע *nirtza*, meaning even if
it hadn't said ואף *v'af*. Oh, yeah, it could have done that,
I suppose. Okay, now, so that's anyway how you know she's not
עובדת את הבן ולא את הבת *ovedes es haben v'lo es habas*.
הנרצע והנמכר לעובד כוכבים אינו עובד לא את הבן ולא את הבת
*Hanirtza v'hanimkar l'oved kochavim einu oved lo es haben v'lo es habas*.
Similarly, well, נרצע *nirtza* we just said and we assumed, now we're
going to prove it, but until now we've been, right? So this
we did yesterday, this is because one פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says שש
שנים shanim, יעבוד *sheish shanim ya'avod*, okay, this is not working? One
פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* says שש שנים shanim, יעבוד *sheish shanim ya'avod*,
which means regardless, and this is ועבדתך *va'avodsecha*, only you. Okay, so
that's how we say there is a six-year that continues after the
person dies, but for others not. אמה עבריה ama ivriya *amah ivriya*,
we said this you learn out because it says ואף לאמתך *v'af
l'amascha*,
which we link to the נרצע *nirtza*, so she's not עובדת את
הבן ולא את הבת *ovedes es haben v'lo es habas*. And now
we're going to have to prove how we know the נרצע *nirtza*
is not עובדת את הבן ואת הבת *ovedes es haben v'es habas*,
which we had just assumed for this דרשה *drasha*. Okay, and also
somebody who is sold to a non-Jew. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says, הנרצע והנמכר לעובד כוכבים אינו עובד לא את הבן ולא
את הבת *Hanirtza v'hanimkar l'oved kochavim einu oved lo es haben v'lo
es habas*. נרצע *Nirtza*, the נרצע *nirtza*, דכתיב dechsiv *dechativ*, ורצע אדוניו
את אזנו במרצע *v'ratza adonav es ozno bamarzea*, she pierced the hole
the ear with you know with an awl, ועבדו לעולם *v'avado l'olam*.
ועבדו לעולם *V'avado l'olam*, ולא את הבן ולא את הבת *v'lo es
haben v'lo es habas*. Okay, so it's interesting, although it says לעולם
*l'olam*, we limit the לעולם *l'olam* number one about יובל Yovel, *Yovel*,
and number two we limit it to only when the master is
alive. Okay, so how do we know this is not because it
says ועבדו לעולם *v'avado l'olam*?
Okay, so that's only the master. The only reason this goes to
the son is because it has שש שנים shanim, יעבוד *sheish shanim
ya'avod*, which is regardless of who he's serving, and this because it's
linked to the עבד עברי eved Ivri *eved ivri*. All right, so
that's how you know the נרצע *nirtza*. נמכר לעובד כוכבים מנין *Nimkar
l'oved kochavim minayin*? אמר חזקיה Chizkiya אמר קרא *Amar Chizkiya amar kra*,
the verse says, וחישב עם קונהו konahu *v'chishav im konehu*. This is
about buying the person back who sells himself to a non-Jew, you
should like you know you should do the accounting assessing with the
purchaser, and to buy back, to buy him back, ולא עם יורשי
קונהו *v'lo im yorshei konehu*, only with קונהו *konehu*, but you don't
have to do it with the heirs because once the guy dies,
the slave goes free. All right, אמר רבא Rava, *Amar Rava*, now
again, you could have said maybe with the heirs you're not entitled
to buy him back, but anyway, that's the דרשה *drasha*. אמר רבא
Rava *Amar Rava*, דבר תורה d'var Torah... עובד כוכבים יורש את אביו
*devar torah oved kochavim yoresh es aviv*. Now we're going to digress
a little bit. Okay, so basically Rava's point is going to be
the fact that you had to tell me that the slave doesn't
serve the heir when he's bought by a non-Jew shows me that
in principle there are laws of inheritance by non-Jews, because without this
exclusion, I would have said he would have had to continue to
serve the heir. One minute, עובד כוכבים יורש את אביו שנאמר וחישב
עם קונהו ולא עם יורשי קונהו *oved kochavim yoresh es aviv shene'emar
v'chishav im konehu v'lo im yorshei konehu*. The fact that we had
to exclude the עבד עברי eved Ivri *eved ivri* from serving the
heirs, מכלל דאית ליה יורשין *michlal d'is lei yorshin*, you see as
a general rule he would have heirs. Okay, גר ger את אביו
עובד כוכבים אינו מדברי תורה Torah. אלא ela, מדברי סופרים *Ger es
aviv oved kochavim einu midevrei torah ela midevrei sofrim*. Now let's say
somebody converts. So he's כקטן שנולד kekatan shenolad. דמי *k'katan shenolad dami*,
which means that legally
his non-Jewish father is no longer legally his father, which means that
legally when the father dies, he doesn't inherit from his father. Okay,
so that's the הלכה halacha *halacha*, he's like קטן שנולד katan she-nold
*katan shenolad*. אינו מדברי תורה Torah אלא ela, מדברי סופרים *Einu midevrei
torah ela midevrei sofrim*, but rabbinically he does. דתנן Detnan... *Detnan*, גר
ger ועובד כוכבים שירשו את אביהם עובד כוכבים *ger v'oved kochavim sheyarshu
es avihem oved kochavim*. Okay, so you had two children who are
non-Jews, one converted, one did not. Okay, so you have Shimon and
Christopher, they're brothers. Okay, so their father died. All right, now in
the estate, what you have is the following: שירשו את אביהם עובד
כוכבים *sheyarshu es avihem oved kochavim*, they are now inheriting from their
non-Jewish father. גר יכול לומר לעובד כוכבים *Ger yachol lomar l'oved kochavim*,
so the convert can say to the non-Jew, טול אתה עבודת כוכבים
ואני מעות *tol ata avodas kochavim v'ani maos*. You know what? You
keep all the idols and I'm מעות *maos*. idols in dad's estate
and I'll just take the cash, okay? טול אתה יינך,
you keep all the wine which he used for עבודה זרה avodah
zarah purposes and it's אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. The point about both
the idols and the wine is we're not talking about just סתם
יינם, stam yaynam, but about יין נסך. yayin nesech. It's אסור בהנאה.
assur b'hana'ah. ואני פירות, va'ani peros, I'll take some of the fruit.
Okay, that's they can divide it up that way. That's acceptable. משבאו
לרשות גר, mishebau l'reshus ger, however once let's say the גר took
possession of it, okay, they both basically took possession of the estate,
אסור, assur, then they cannot divide the property because then basically they
cannot, he cannot say, "You know what? I took this half, but
I have some idols here, here, you take idols and give me
the money for it," because then basically he's selling idols for money
or he's selling יין נסך yayin nesech for money. So if they
divided it before they took possession, then this was just the half
that he got. He got the half that didn't have the idols
in it. But after he took possession, he's basically selling the idols
for money.
So what's that, what's that תוספתא Tosefta teaching us? You have to
be smart.
Yes. Now, no, what it's also teaching us is that what we'll
see it's teaching us. So it's teaching us the following point. It
says, well,
first one thing first of all, it could be teaching us is
like אין ברירה. ein breira. Because why don't you say that even
if they divide afterwards, איגלאי מלתא למפרע, igallai milta l'mafrea, that that
was always his? Okay, so we don't say that. So now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: One minute, says the גמרא, Gemara ואי
סלקא דעתך דאורייתא, v'ei salka deitach d'Oraisa, if he inherits his father
biblically, his non-Jewish father, כי לא באו לרשותו נמי, ki lo bau
l'reshuso nami,
so even if before they took possession of it, as soon as
the father dies, כי שרי, ki sharei, but nevertheless as soon as
the father dies, they're now equal in heirs of the estate and
now if they divide in a particular way, effectively what they're saying
is, "I'll sell you my half in the idols for your half
in the something else." So it would be a problem even before
they actually took physical possession of it. It's still, it's theirs, they
inherited it. Okay, חילופי עבודה זרה קא שקיל, chilufei avodah zarah ka
shakil, you're taking in exchange for an idol. So what difference does
it make if you've taken physical possession or not physical possession? Either
way, you inherited it and now you're swapping your idols for money.
So what difference should it make? אלא מדרבנן, ela mi-d'rabbanan, it must
be that he only inherits it rabbinically, and therefore if it's only
rabbinic, when the father died, they didn't make it that he automatically
owned it. They did in a way that gave him the latitude
to make sure he got the permissible part. So he's not considered
to be to inherit it to take possession of it until he
takes physical possession of it. But if it was biblical, he would
have taken possession of it as soon as the father died.
Yeah, that's a very interesting... is this correct, that there's a legal
distinction of, "I have inherited this car, but I don't own it
yet"? What? Can you make that legal distinction, like I'm the...
Well, you can't biblically. You can only, you could only do it
rabbinically. Meaning, rabbinically, you could say if it was biblical, as soon
as the father died, they inherited it, they owned it, and then
any type of swapping, you'd be getting הנאה hana'ah from עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. So the fact that the, that there's a space, the
fact that there's a space
between death and taking possession, can only work at a rabbinic level.
Very interesting distinction. Right. Now, תוספות Tosafos points out, why doesn't the
whole thing work because of יש ברירה? yesh breira? Maybe it can
work because... so look at the תוספות, Tosafos, חילופי עבודה זרה קא
שקיל ואין לומר טעמא משום ברירה, chilufei avodah zarah ka shakil v'ein
lomar ta'ama mishum breira, that, no, maybe it's okay because if we
swap it, then in the end that was always my estate that
I was inheriting. כלומר השתא הוברר הדבר דזה חלקו, klomar hashta hovrar
hadavar d'ze chelko, you can't say that, that that's why it works
if we do it before we take physical possession. דאם כן אפילו
באו לרשותו נמי אימא מהאי טעמא, d'im ken afilu bau l'reshuso nami
eima mehai ta'ama, even after they took
physical possession, right, they went over, they took all the boxes out
of their father's house, they put it in the van, they drove
it to their house, and then they split it there. They opened
it up and then the idols... So say יש ברירה yesh breira
there too? They have not yet divided it just because they took
physical possession. So the point here is it's not that it's impossible
that that could work in a ירושה yerusha context because of יש
ברירה. yesh breira. The point is that there's a difference between the
moment they inherit it and the moment they take physical possession. And
that doesn't make any sense at a דאורייתא d'Oraisa level. So it
must show you that it's only, the inheritance is only מדרבנן mi-d'rabbanan
and the rabbis opened up that space in order to allow him
to do it in a way that he would not have to
take possession of the idols. Yes.
Two questions. Is it even, is it permissible even for a non-Jew
to benefit from עבודה זרה? avodah zarah?
Yeah, that's a good point. I mean, you're saying like, why isn't
it like לפני עור? lifnei iver? But there's only an איסור issur
for a non-Jew to worship עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, not to actually
own or be נהנה ne'eneh from עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But that's
a good, very good point.
Second question, back to the issue of the Gentile inheriting from a
father. There are statements in סנהדרין Sanhedrin that state there are no
paternal relations for non-Jews.
What? One more time?
There are statements in סנהדרין Sanhedrin that there are no paternal relations
for non-Jews.
You sure you're not talking about slaves? You're talking about non-Jews?
No, I'm... for instance, a Gentile can marry a paternal half-sister.
No, that's not that there are no... well, there is a question
about what defines עריות, arayos, but that does not mean that we
don't recognize family structure and parentage. That's a different point. It's a
question about what's included in the איסור עריות. Isur Arayot. Okay? So
that's not... but yes, it's relevant, but it's not exactly the same.
Aren't the גמרא Gemara pages filled with crosses and all that?
Yes, that's a different story. Moving on. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this. So okay, so it's only דרבנן. derabbanan. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אלא מדרבנן. ela miderabbanan. Now why is it דרבנן?
derabbanan? Why did they let the Jew inherit? Maybe they should have
said, you know, you don't want to make it confusing, now he's
going to feel that he's still, you know, maybe part of this
non-Jewish family or something? גזירה הוא דעבדו רבנן. gezeirah hi de’avdu rabanan.
The rabbis did it because it was a protection. What was the
protection? שמא יחזור לסורו. shema yachzor lesoro. If this now-convert would find
out he's not going to inherit his non-Jewish father's estate, he's going
to say, forget this being Jewish, I'm going to go back to
the other religion. Now הלכתית halachically he would still be Jewish, but
maybe the other faith would take him back and that would rect-
the other faith would recognize him and he'd be able to inherit.
Okay, so therefore we had to... we had to prevent that. תניא
נמי הכי. Tanya nami hachi. We taught similarly: במה דברים אמורים כשיורשו,
Bameh devarim amurim kesheyorsho, אבל כשנשתתפו אסור. aval keshenishtatfu asur. When is
it true that we allow him to divide? When they inherit before
taking possession. But if he was in a partnership with a non-Jew,
then you can't divide because then again you're sw- you're exchanging your
half of this איסור הנאה issur hana'ah for money. Okay, so that
again just shows that this ירושה yerushah is a special case. Anyway,
עובד כוכבים את הגר. Oved kochavim et hager. So that's anyway a
non-Jew inheriting a... a גר inheriting his non-Jewish father.
עובד כוכבים את הגר...
Oved kochavim
et hager...
כשנשתתפו Keshenishtatfu could be like for instance if there is an estate
there we're going to buy it out, you can still say we're
going to put in a hundred dollars, your fifty will go...
Yeah, there's ways you could do it, but it wouldn't make a
difference between ownership and possession. Okay. עובד כוכבים את הגר וגר את
הגר. Oved kochavim et hager veger et hager. Now how about a
non-Jew inheriting his father the convert? How could that be? That's a
person who already has a child, a non-Jew already has a child,
the father converts, the child does not. Okay. So then this Jewish
convert dies, his non-Jewish child does not inherit from him. Okay. עובד
כוכבים את הגר וגר את הגר, Oved kochavim et hager veger et
hager, or a father and a son both in- converted together. But
legally they're not related now. Okay? They're both כקטן שנולד. And the
father dies, the son does not inherit. Okay? וגר את הגר אינו
לא מדין תורה ולא מדין סופרים. Veger et hager eino lo midin
Torah velo midin soferim. So a- the- it's not- there's not going
to be inheritance because nobody is legally related, and there wasn't a
דרבנן derabbanan nee- need to create inheritance, so we just let it
at the דין תורה. din Torah.
Well, why not have a דרבנן derabbanan inheritance?
What? Why would we? The only reason before was to prevent...
which we usually do.
In other words, we- we don't normally דרבנן-ly derabbanan create inheritance. The
only... אדרבא. aderabba. The point is we don't want there to be
confusion over the legal status here. It is a confusing legal status.
People are biologically related and not legally related. And if that gets
confused it could be a- a big problem. Somebody would think it
has a נפקא מינה nafka mina for יבום, yibbum, other types of
נפקא מינה-s. nafka mina So creating inheritance actually muddies the waters. Why
should we create inheritance? Just let let the normal laws of inheritance
apply. The only exception we made was the one case of the
convert with the non-Jewish father because of שמא יחזור לסורו... shema yachzor
lesoro... ככולה? kekulah? No, שמא יחזור לסורו. shema yachzor lesoro. Okay.
דתנן... לוה מעות של גר שנתגייר הוא ובניו. loveh ma'ot shel ger
shenitgayer hu uvanav. So you borrowed money from a convert who converted
with his sons. So they all converted together but legally not related.
Okay. לא יחזיר לבניו. Lo yachzir levanav. Don't pay the- the debt
back to the sons. The sons... if the guy dies, the sons
are not his heirs. ואם החזיר אין רוח חכמים נוחה הימנו. Ve’im
hechzir ein ruach chachamim nocha heimenu. And if you paid it back,
actually the rabbis are not happy with you. So that to me
sounds like it's a bad thing. Now רש״י Rashi actually makes it
sound like אין רוח חכמים נוחה הימנו ein ruach chachamim nocha heimenu
means... means like you don't get any יישר כח. yasher koach. You
didn't do necessarily a good thing, but not necessarily that you did
a bad thing. But the simple language is that they're not happy
with it. And the reason they're not happy with it is for
what I just said to Michael, which is like what big deal,
so okay, I could have kept the money, so I gave it
to them. I wanted to do a nice thing. But the point
is that it could muddy the waters. Like, you know, רש״י Rashi
says, let's say he's got a brother, you know, well, it'd be
funny about a brother case because he wouldn't actually have a legal...
Anyway, but the point is it could muddy the waters and it's
important to know legally how people are considered to be legally related.
Okay. והתניא... Vehatanya... the גמרא Gemara says, but didn't we teach in
a ברייתא... braita... רוח חכמים נוחה הימנו. ruach chachamim nocha heimenu. Actually
the rabbis are happy with you if you pay back the children.
You might not be legally obligated, but it's the right thing to
do. So the גמרא Gemara, says, לא קשיא. la kashya. כאן שהורתו
ולידתו שלא בקדושה וכאן שהורתו שלא בקדושה ולידתו בקדושה. Kan shehorato velidato
shelo bikhdusha vekan shehorato shelo bikhdusha velidato bikhdusha. The question is like
this: in what way is he not legally related to his children?
So there are two scenarios. One scenario is the child is already
born and the father and the child son both convert. That's הורתו
ולידתו שלא בקדושה. horato velidato shelo bikhdusha. The son was born before
anybody was Jewish. Okay? That's one case where they're very clearly not
related to one another legally at least. How about the other case?
A man and his wife and his pregnant wife convert. Okay? Man
and his wife and his pregnant wife convert. The child is born
Jewish because when the mother converts she's Jewish and therefore the child
is considered to be part of the conversion of the mother, whatever,
anyway the child is born Jewish. Okay? Whom is the child Whom
is the child? Not conceived Jewish, הורתו שלא בקדושה ולידתו בקדושה. horato
she-lo b'kedusha v'lidato b'kedusha. So there is no question, of course he's
Jewish. Whom is the child related to? Now, so the הלכה halacha
is that, meaning is there the parentage? Because that's what we're dealing
about parentage. The child's mother is legally his mother because after the
conversion, after the mother dunks in the מקוה, mikvah, the child has
continued to gestate in the mother's womb and therefore
she was pregnant. Man and his pregnant wife convert. Okay? The child
is then born. הורתו שלא בקדושה ולידתו בקדושה. horato she-lo b'kedusha v'lidato
b'kedusha.
Whom is this child related to? He's related to his mother because
after the conversion he continues to grow in his mother's womb and
therefore that considers mother continues to be in that sort of mother
capacity vis-a-vis him, to be an interesting question about how this relates
to concepts about surrogate motherhood. Anyway, so then he's born, even though
he was קטן שנולד katan she-nold at the moment that they dunked
in the מקוה, mikvah, but the ongoing growing being in his mother's
womb or whatever, he is now considered to be his mother's child
legally, but he's not his father's child because the father stepped out
of the picture biologically after the moment of conception. Okay? So therefore
once he was converted and once they dunked in the מקוה, mikvah,
at that stage he was קטן שנולד and no new relationship was
established with the father. So this child is born Jewish, related to
his Jewish mother but not legally related to his Jewish father. Okay?
And the relevance of that would be one area where that would
be relevant would be well let's say it would be what do
you call it would be inheritance. Okay? So the father dies, this
child legally does not inherit. So in both cases the child does
not inherit, but in one case the child looks much more Jewish,
much more like a natural sort of Jewish child born Jewish part
of a Jewish family structure etc. than in the other case. So
the הלכה halacha. says in one of these you're supposed to pay
in both you're not legally obligated and in both the child is
not legally related to the father, but in one it's a good
thing to pay back and the other it's not. So in which
one is it a good thing to pay back? So there was
an early version of רש״י Rashi which we don't have, but תוספות
Tosafot quote that רש״י Rashi said the good thing to pay back
was the kid who had הורתו שלא בקדושה ולידתו בקדושה. horato she-lo
b'kedusha v'lidato b'kedusha. That's like closer to the real thing so you
should pay him back. Okay? But תוספות Tosafot says no אדרבה, adderaba,
that's the one you shouldn't pay back because that's the one that's
more easy to confuse because if you go ahead and people will
actually think that the father is the legal father because that's the
one that they converted and then the mother was maybe three months
pregnant, it looks like that's a normal case of being the legal
father. So because that's more easy to confuse דווקא davka that's the
one that you shouldn't do a good deed and pay back because
that'll just confuse people more. The one that's more obviously not legally
the father is the one that it would be okay to pay
back. Yes.
Question about the second case.
If
the man and his wife convert, are they supposed to remarry, getting
married as Jews? Yes. Yes. And we actually do that. And actually
there's also a הלכה halacha that if a man and wife convert
about keeping them apart for three months or some פוסקים poskim say
you can use a pregnancy test because you want to determine whether
if she's already pregnant then there would be this נפקא מינה nafka
mina that the child would not legally be related to the father.
So you want to determine is the mother pregnant at the time
of conversion. So according to the גמרא Gemara you're supposed to wait
three months but some פוסקים poskim say you could just do a
pregnancy test.
So regarding all this muddying the waters, wouldn't you say as the
father supports a son because then he'll think that the Jewish family
according to his Jewish
I mean that's an interesting point. You mean like why don't we
start worrying about cases about adoption for example and all these other
types of cases? Yeah I understand, it's a good question. I mean
obviously you could say that it's more confusing because it was he
is a biological child not just being like raised. But yeah I
mean I hear the point but I think like the point about
inheritance,
I mean people do take in children. The point about inheritance
is really something like the big one big נפקא מינה nafka mina
of being a legal father is the issue of inheritance so presumably
that was the one that we're most concerned about. But yeah I
hear the point.
Any נפקא מינה nafka mina for אבילות aveilut as well?
Right, right. Well yeah I mean we do allow in cases of
adoptive parents or whatever to do like to do forms of אבילות
aveilut and so on. I mean you're saying would it muddy the
water...
Yeah I understand.
Well first of all once the father's already dead it's a little
well I hear your point. Here too the father is dead. Yeah
I don't know, those are really good questions, those are really good
questions. Yeah.
I actually know someone whom the local rabbis forbade from observing any
אבילות aveilut for her adoptive father for that reason? I was I
was stunned.
Because of this type of a reason? Yeah. The general position is
that you let somebody could say קדיש, kaddish, could keep אבילות, aveilut,
like the one thing is because most of those things don't compromise
other הלכות. halachot. The one thing that you that you wouldn't do
is like the ניחומי אנינות nichumei aninut which is like not doing
מצוות, mitzvot, because that does compromise other הלכות. halachot. Okay anyway let's
go on.
Okay. רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רבי יוחנן עובד כוכבים יורש את
אביו דבר תורה. Rabbi Chiya bar Abin amar Rabbi Yochanan oved kochavim
yoresh et aviv dvar Torah. Now we're going to just before we
just inferred it from a דרשה that he would exclude the case
of the עבד eved serving the heir of the... of the non-Jew.
But here he's going to say it's a פסוק pasuk that there's
inheritance. Okay, דכתיב the verse says,
כי ירושה לעשו נתתי את הר שעיר. Ki yerushah l'Eisav nasati es
Har Seir. I've given הר שעיר Har Seir as a bequest, you
know, bequest as an inheritance to עשו. Eisav. ודילמא ישראל מומר שאני,
V'dilma Yisrael mumar shani, says the גמרא, Gemara aye, so then is
he really a non-Jew? He's a ישראל מומר Yisrael mumar because he
was born to יצחק. Yitzchak. Okay, so anyway, that's an interesting perception.
אלא מהכא, Ela mehacha, כי לבני לוט נתתי את ער ירושה. Ki
livnei Lot nasati es Ar yerushah. So לוט Lot was not a
descendant of אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב Yaakov and he also
gets an inheritance. For רב חייא בר אבין Rav Chiya bar Avin
מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבא? mai taama lo amar k'Rava? Okay, so
why did רב חייא בר אבין Rav Chiya bar Avin not say
like רבא, Rava who was this, one minute, let me just check
the דבר תורה... d'var Torah
one minute, which was this?
If it's וחשיב עם קונהו, v'chishav im konahu, there are different פסוקים.
psukim. Right, oh yes, one says וחשיב עם קונהו v'chishav im konahu
and the other says ועבדו לעולם ולא את הבן. va'avado l'olam v'lo
es haben. Right, thank you. So why didn't he say כרבא? k'Rava?
Because
וחשיב עם קונהו, v'chishav im konahu, מי כתיב וחשיב עם קונהו ולא
עם יורשי קונהו? mi ksiv v'chishav im konahu v'lo im yorshei konahu?
Because קונהו does not have that exclusion, that sense of excluding the
יורשים. yorshim. Okay, and רבא Rava מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב חייא
בר אבין mai taama lo amar k'Rav Chiya bar Avin who said
that it was ועבדו ולא ליורשים, va'avado v'lo l'yorshim, which at least
there it more speaks directly about whom are you serving, right, so
that is a little bit more relevant. So he
says, משום כבודו דאברהם שאני. mishum k'vodo d'Avraham shani. What? Hold on,
I'm making...
wait, that's why he won't get it, not because דבר תורה Torah
יורש בכולו. yoresh b'kulu. Whoa whoa whoa hold on hold
on hold on hold on.
No, חזקיה said וחשיב עם קונהו ולא עם יורשי קונהו. v'chishav im
konahu v'lo im yorshei konahu.
Oh no no no, we're just doing with what is the פסוק
pasuk? that you learn it from, right, I'm sorry. We're not dealing
with the question about the עבד, eved, I got confused. Okay, we're
dealing with the question, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, we're dealing with the
question about how do you know that a non-Jew inherits from his
father? Okay, so let's do that again, I'm sorry. רב חייא בר
אבין Rav Chiya bar Avin מאי טעמא לא אמר כרבא? mai taama
lo amar k'Rava? Why did he not say like רבא Rava that
you know that he inherits his father because it had to exclude
an עבד עברי eved Ivri. from serving the son? Because he says
no, מי כתיב וחשיב עם קונהו ולא עם יורשי קונהו? mi ksiv
v'chishav im konahu v'lo im yorshei konahu? It's not so clear. I'd
much rather quote an explicit פסוק that calls it a ירושה. yerushah.
I'm not going to be inferring an idea of ירושה yerushah because
of an exclusion of an עבד עברי eved Ivri serving the son,
that's not clear in the פסוק. I'd rather quote an explicit פסוק
about a ירושה. yerushah. For רבא מאי טעמא לא אמר כרב חייא
בר אבין? mai taama lo amar k'Rav Chiya bar Avin? So why
did רבא not say like רב חייא בר אבין, Rav Chiya bar
Avin, it is an explicit פסוק? So he says, משום כבודו דאברהם
שאני. mishum k'vodo d'Avraham shani. No, because maybe for the honor of
אברהם Avraham we allowed his, you know, his nephew to have this
inheritance and his descendants of his nephew. But that doesn't prove that
as a general rule there are rules of inheritance by non-Jews. Okay,
but in the end of the day everybody agrees that that is
true. Okay, תנו רבנן, tana rabanan, now back to עבד עברי. eved
Ivri יש בעברי שאין בעבריה ויש בעבריה שאין בעברי. Yesh b'Ivri she'ein
b'Ivriyah v'yesh b'Ivriyah she'ein b'Ivri. There are rules that apply to an
עבד עברי eved ivri. and not an אמה עבריה, ama ivriya. and
the reverse. Now, we've already seen some of them, but this list
is going to be very different than the list we've seen before.
יש בעברי שהוא יוצא בשנים וביובל ובמיתת האדון, Yesh b'Ivri shehu yotzei
b'shanim u'v'yovel u'v'misas ha'adon, an עברי Ivri goes out in שנים, shanim,
יובל, Yovel, and the מיתת האדון, misas ha'adon, מה שאין כן בעבריה,
ma she'ein kein b'Ivriyah, which is not true of the עבריה. Ivriyah.
And if I still have my chart I'd say what? We said
that an עברי Ivri goes out in שנים, shanim, goes out in
יובל, Yovel, goes out in מיתת האדון misas ha'adon actually, right, and
goes out בסימנים b'simanim actually. I mean, right, the only thing that
is different is the נרצע מיתת האדון. misas ha'adon. Okay, or בסימנים,
b'simanim, but all of this had been the same. Okay, and the
fact that it's explicitly excluding מיתת האדון misas ha'adon is bizarre, you
know, but anyway, but all of that we had said was the
same. Okay, so that's point number one. מה
שאין כן בעבריה. Ma she'ein kein b'Ivriyah. ויש בעבריה שהרי עבריה יוצאה
בסימנים. V'yesh b'Ivriyah she'harei Ivriyah yotzei b'simanim. Okay, well that's fine, that
she goes out בסימנים, b'simanim, that we know is only by the
עבריה. Ivriyah. But here's another הלכה. halacha. ויש בעבריה שהרי...
let me see that... מה שאין כן בעברי, ma she'ein kein b'Ivri,
ויש בעבריה שהרי עבריה יוצאה בסימנים v'yesh b'Ivriyah she'harei Ivriyah yotzei b'simanim
ואינה נמכרת לשנית, v'einah nimkeres l'shneis, she cannot be sold twice, and
an עבד עברי eved ivri can be sold twice. So that's a
new discussion which we haven't seen yet. ומפדין אותה על כרחו, U'mifdin
osah al karcho, and she can be redeemed against his will, presumably
against the master's will, מה שאין כן בעברי, which is also bizarre,
because until now we've seen that the idea of גירעון כסף giron
kesef is that you can buy back your freedom against the will
of the master. So this whole ברייתא braisa is like every... is
like either new or against what we have been assuming and saying
until now. So let's take a look. אמר מר יש בעברי שאין
בעבריה. Amar Mar, Yesh b'Ivri she'ein b'Ivriyah. Okay, ורמינהו, u'remini, so first
it sounds like it's only שנים, shanim יובל, Yovel, and מיתת האדון
misas ha'adon is only by an עברי. Ivri. Really?
ורמינהו, u'remini, יתירה עליו אמה עבריה yeseirah alav amah Ivriyah ו'אמר משנה
v'amar mishna she... קונה עצמה בסימנים. koneh atzmah b'simanim. She has all
the ways of an עברי Ivri plus בסימנים, b'simanim, and you're telling
me not שנים, shanim not יובל, yovel. none of this? Now, by
the way, the גמרא's Gemara going to find a way to reconcile
it, but this really could reflect a different תנאי Tannaic position because
all of the פסוקים, psukim, if you think about... But what do
the פסוקים psukim say by the אמה עבריה? ama ivriya There are
the פסוקים psukim that speak about ואם לבנו ייעדנה כמשפט הבנות יעשה
לה, v'im livno yi'adena k'mishpat habanot ya'aseh lah, אם אחרת יקח לו
im acheret yikach lo whatever you know לא ימשל למכרה בבגדו בה.
lo yimshol l'mochrah b'vigdo bah. Says there it doesn't talk about anyway
in which you know it says that if he doesn't do ייעוד
yi'ud she goes free. It doesn't explain how. Okay, so it does
say והפדה. v'hapdah. So there you could say that סימנים simanim and
פדיון, pidyon, but it doesn't mention שנים, shanim it doesn't mention יובל.
yovel שנים shanim and יובל yovel. are in the פסוקים psukim basically
by the עבד עברי. eved ivri, Okay, so now it is true
by the case of the by the case of the הענקה, it
says ואף לאמתך תעשה כן and that's a context of six years,
but it never explicitly says אמה עבריה ama ivriya by six years
or יובל. yovel? So this ברייתא braita might just represent a different
tradition, but the גמרא Gemara is going to find a way to
reconcile it.
But that's common, right? Right, now we have a משנה, mishna,
but okay, so let's see what the גמרא Gemara. says. אמר רב
ששת Amar Rav Sheshet so so how do we deal with this
fact this ברייתא braita says she doesn't go free by שנים shanim
and יובל? yovel. אמר רב ששת Amar Rav Sheshet כגון שייעדה. k'gon
she'yi'ada. No, no, no, this ברייתא braita is talking about after ייעוד.
yi'ud. If the master does ייעוד yi'ud and marries her, then she
doesn't go free with שנים shanim and יובל. yovel. Well, that's pretty
obvious. גמרא Gemara. says ייעדה פשיטא גיטא בעיא. yi'ada peshita gita ba'aya.
Of course she needs a גט. get. Not she doesn't go free
with שנים shanim and יובל. yovel No, מהו דתימא לא ליבטלו הלכתא
מינה. ma d'teima lo livatel hilchata mina. No, because I might have
thought that ייעוד yi'ud entitles her to take her as a wife
and to get sort of you know sexual you know to have
sex with her and whatever, but maybe she's still a slave wife,
right? So maybe she could still you know you could sort of
free her by the same paths of freeing her as a slave
and not give her a גט get and once six years come
or the יובל yovel come, maybe that's only a relationship in the
context of slavery. Okay, I mean if you think about it, right,
the הלכה Halacha. is that an עבד עברי Eved Ivri the master
gives him a שפחה כנענית shifcha kena'anit to have children by and
that's a relationship that exists in the context of slavery. So maybe
this wouldn't have been a total קידושין kiddushin and it would have
been
מהו דתימא לא ליבטלו הלכתא מינה ma d'teima lo livatel hilchata mina
mean
the status of a slave, the status of a אמה עבריה. Amah
Ivriyah,
Right, maybe this whole ייעוד yi'ud is in the context of slavery.
קמשמע לן kamashma l'an that it's not. That once it's ייעוד yi'ud
she becomes an אשת איש eshet ish and the other ways of
becoming free do not apply. Okay, אי הכי אמאי יוצא בסימנים? I
hachi amai yotza b'simanim? So but what does it mean that she
goes free with סימנים? simanim? She doesn't go free with סימנים, simanim,
she only goes free with a גט. get. הכי קאמר אם לא
ייעדה יוצאה אף בסימנים. hachi ka'amar im lo yi'ada yotza af b'simanim.
But if he didn't do ייעוד yi'ud then all the ways of
freedom apply plus סימנים. simanim. It's a radical
it's a good read. It's a you think it's a good read?
It says she doesn't go free with שנים shanim and יובל yovel
but she does go free with סימנים. simanim. It's contrasting יובל yovel
and שנים to סימנים. simanim. And what we're saying is she doesn't
go free with שנים and יובל yovel once there was ייעוד, yi'ud,
but if there wasn't ייעוד yi'ud she does go free with them
and with סימנים. simanim. I think that's a pretty bad read.
Anyway, okay, but that's what we're reading so it was an interesting
הוה אמינא hava amina that ייעוד yi'ud would be in the context
of עבדות avdut and not a fundamental transformation to קידושין. kiddushin. By
the way, that's really the חידוש chidush of the Torah. The Torah
says, right, שארה כסותה ועונתה לא יגרע she'era k'suta v'onata lo yigra
means just because she became your wife through עבדות avdut she doesn't
have any fewer rights than a full wife. Okay, so that's but
anyway but that's sort of what it's saying maybe would have been
a הוה אמינא hava amina but what it's really doing is taking
a ברייתא braita that really is a very different approach and sees
אמה עבריה Amah Ivriyah in a totally different category, right, and doesn't
have שנים and doesn't have יובל Yovel and so on and it's
trying to reconcile it and say it's the same. I actually have
to tell you that besides the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim
are consistent this ברייתא braita is consistent with פשט pshat of the
פסוקים, psukim, there's something attractive to this because it again makes the
status of אמה עבריה Amah Ivriya less about עבדות. avdut. If you
think about it this girl's working under twelve years old. How much
work are you going to get out of her? Now I suppose
in the old days, you know, they would train the girls young
and she could do a lot of work in the kitchen between
six and twelve. So maybe, but nevertheless it makes it something completely
different if the fewer overlap of laws that exist between those two
categories.
Where do we get סימנים simanim exactly? What? סימנים. simanim. From where?
Just because it's clear from the פסוקים psukim that if he doesn't
do ייעוד yi'ud then she's ויצאה חנם אין כסף. v'yatza chinam ein
kasef. So what's the ויצאה? v'yatza? So אין כסף ein kasef it's
not והפדה, v'hapdah, so what's the ויצאה חנם? v'yatza chinam? And then
it could be six years but that's not in the context. It
sounds like you had the chance to do ייעוד, yi'ud, you didn't
do ייעוד, yi'ud, she goes free.
And doing ייעוד yi'ud would be when she has סימנים? simanim?
Prior to her having סימנים. simanim. Right, but the חז"ל Chazal read
the סימנים simanim as the trigger there, but it's clear in the
פסוקים psukim that after the opportunity of ייעוד yi'ud at some point
she goes free.
One other question that stayed what I don't understand fully from yesterday
is we know we can't be מוחל mochel on the on the
חוב chov of the עבד עברי, Eved Ivri but let's say he's
just like doing a real bad job? You can't like fire him?
Like he's messing up... No, you can't. That's שטר שחרור. shtar shichrur.
Okay, although right yeah presumably people don't disagree to the שטר shtar
although תוספות Tosafot had a question because it wasn't in the משנה.
mishna. All right. It's a bad read but you like the ברייתא.
braita. I no I like the ברייתא braita I don't the reconcile
read is a bad read. Okay. ואין למאן כרת ונארשת. V'ein l'min
kares v'ne'ershet. Now here's a new הלכה. halacha The bad read, but
you like the ברייתא Braisa read. No, I like the ברייתא—the Braisa
reconcile read is a bad read. Okay. אינה נמכרת ונשנית. Eina nimkeret
v'nishnet. Now he has a new הלכה. She cannot be resold but
an עבד עברי Eved Ivri. can be resold. מכלל דעבד עברי נמכר
ונשנה? Mikhlal d'Eved Ivri nimkar v'nishneh? Sounds like an עבד עברי Eved
Ivri can be
resold? והתניא תנא בברייתא, Ve'ha'tanya t'na b'Braisa, בגניבתו, Begneivato,
ונמכר בגניבתו V'nimkar begneivato ולא בכפלו. v'lo b'khiflo. Let's say the guy
has enough money he steals something or he robs rather and he
has enough money to pay the principal back but not to pay
the fine which is double the price. Okay. So now he stole
something worth a thousand dollars, he has to pay two thousand. So
he can pay it back a thousand. Would you sell him as
a slave so that to pay back the other thousand that he
owes? The answer is no.
And he just has to pay it back
whenever he gets it, it's an outstanding debt. בגניבתו ולא בזממו. Begneivato
v'lo b'zimamo. Let's say somebody is an עד זומם ed zomem on
somebody who's a גנב. ganav. Say somebody testifies somebody was a גנב
ganav and owed ten thousand dollars and they were proven to be
עדים זוממין. edim zomemin. So now they owe ten thousand dollars. They
don't have the money. Can you sell them in slavery to pay
it up? No. Only if you're the actual גנב, ganav, not if
you're an עד זומם ed zomem for a גנב. ganav. You might
have said כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו, ka'asher zamam la'asot l'achiv, and it
has the same consequence of being sold into slavery. But the answer
is no.
Does the עד זומם ed zomem also have to pay כפל? kefel?
Yeah, exactly. What he would have done to the other guy. בגניבתו,
Begneivato, now here's what's relevant for us, כיון שנמכר פעם אחת שוב
אי אתה רשאי למוכרו. keivan shenimkar pa'am achat shuv i ata rashai
l'mokhro. בגניבתו Begneivato is singular. If he's sold once and not he
be sold multiple times. So you see it's true even about an
עבד עברי. Eved Ivri Now you might say that maybe
that's only by גניבה. gneivah. First of all, it's also the same
way we're contrasting between עבד עברי Eved Ivri and אמה עבריה, Amah
Ivriya it's also important although this has not played out yet to
think about differences between עבד עברי Eved Ivri who's מוכר עצמו mokher
atzmo and עבד עברי Eved Ivri who's נמכר בגניבתו. nimkar begneivato. So
maybe if it's מוכר עצמו mokher atzmo he could sell himself multiple
times, נמכר בגניבתו nimkar begneivato only once. But nevertheless the ברייתא Braisa
said that only an אמה עבריה Amah Ivriya? is not resold and
עבד עברי Eved Ivri is resold. And here it's saying there are
cases an עבד עברי Eved Ivri is not resold. Okay, so let's
take a look. בגניבתו. Begneivato. Okay, שוב אי אתה רשאי למוכרו. shuv
i ata rashai l'mokhro. So אמר רבא לא קשיא כאן בגניבה אחת
כאן בשתי גניבות. amar Rava lo kashya kan b'gneivah achat kan b'shtei
gneivot. One גניבה gneivah or two גניבות. gneivot. Now there's a debate
of רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafos which way the debate goes. I'm going
to read the תוספות Tosafos which is an easier read at least
for our נוסח nusach in the גמרא. Gemara תוספות Tosafos says for
one גניבה gneivah that if you stole something worth a thousand dollars
and your value on the marketplace is only five hundred dollars, I
can sell you and then sell you again. For you can be
sold in slavery for one גניבה gneivah even if it entails multiple
sales. Okay, so you work six years and then you have to
work another six years till you pay off this one גניבה. gneivah.
But if after this event, I know that you understand, I understand,
just because that whatever, רש"י Rashi says the opposite, but let's read
it this way. If after this event you steal again, then you
can never be sold for a second גניבה, gneivah, but you could
be sold multiple times for one. Okay, because גניבה gneivah is singular.
So for one גניבה gneivah you can be sold multiple times, but
you cannot be sold for multiple
גניבות. gneivot. That's the way תוספות Tosafos reads it.
And רש"י Rashi whole מסקנא maskana then, and then he steals some
more?
Maybe, hopefully you've learned your lesson, what can I tell you, an
amateur professional. All right, quiet people, we got to move. Anyway, רש"י
Rashi reads it the opposite way. רש"י Rashi reads it you cannot
be sold two times for one גניבה, gneivah, but you can be
sold one time for each גניבה. gneivah. Okay. Anyway, אמר ליה אביי,
amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said back, בגניבתו טובא משמע. begneivato tuva
mashma. What do you mean? בגניבתו begneivato sounds like multiple, like it
sounds like even if there are separate גניבות gneivot you could be
sold for each time.
I don't know, hold on.
One minute.
Oh, תוספות Tosafos says it sort of anticipates the answer. If you
stole multiple times from one person, well let's just see. It sounds
like even he thinks that even if you steal multiple times from
the same person, it's still like the same act of thieving from
the person or burglary of the person. So אלא, so anyway this
is what תוספות Tosafos reads it, בגניבתו טובא משמע. begneivato tuva mashma.
אלא אמר אביי לא קשיא כאן באדם אחד כאן בשני בני אדם.
ela amar Abaye lo kashya kan b'adam echad kan b'shnei bnei adam.
So תוספות—so Tosafos what that means again according to תוספות Tosafos is,
if you steal once from one person or multiple times from one
person, then you can be—it's all considered one category of גניבה. gneivah.
You're stealing from one person even over multiple times. And therefore you
can be—you can be sold multiple times for one category of גניבה.
gneivah. But for a second category of גניבה gneivah you cannot be
sold. רש"י Rashi says the exact opposite, okay. If you did two
separate גניבות gneivot you could be sold for each one, okay, and
if it's two separate גניבות gneivot from two separate people, you can
be sold for each one. But the more it's brought together, right,
multiple גניבות gneivot from one person, then you cannot be sold multiple
times. All right, so basically it's like if it's considered one category,
one type of גניבה gneivah from one person or whatever, or two
גניבות gneivot from one person, according to תוספות—תוספות says it's when it's
one you can be sold multiple times, when it's multiple you cannot
be sold for different
גניבות, gneivot, okay, and
רש"י... Rashi... Anyway, okay, but there are ways in which that so
is true. There are limits to even an עבד עברי Eved Ivri.
being sold multiple times, but there are definitely cases בין מוכר עצמו
ובין נמכר בגניבתו bein mocher atzmo uvein nimkar bigneivato where he can
be sold multiple times. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan גנב
אלף ושווה חמש מאות ganav elef veshaveh chamesh me'ot you stole something
worth a thousand and you're worth five hundred, נמכר וחוזר ונמכר. nimkar
vechozer venimkar. You could be, this is why תוספות Tosafos said what
he said, because it said you could be sold and sold again
for the same גניבה geneiva to pay it off. Of course, if
you look, the גר״א’s Gra גירסא girsa is נמכר ואינו חוזר ונמכר.
nimkar ve'eino chozer venimkar. So the exact debate of רש״י Rashi תוספות
Tosafos has to do with this גירסא girsa in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay, but we're going to follow our גירסא, girsa, so which is
according to תוספות Tosafot that for one category of גניבה geneiva you
can be sold multiple times. נמכר וחוזר ונמכר. nimkar vechozer venimkar. גנב
חמש מאות ושווה אלף. ganav chamesh me'ot veshaveh elef. Now if you're,
the גניבה geneiva is worth five hundred and you're worth a thousand,
so you're worth more than the גניבה, geneiva, אינו נמכר כלל. eino
nimkar klal. Then you can't be sold. Okay? Then you have to
owe the money, then you have to owe the money. Okay, but
it is not fair to make you serve since the only sort
of duration of servitude is six years, it's not fair to make,
there's not a concept of serving three years. It's not fair to
make you serve more than your debt. Okay, so if your service
doesn't pay off the debt, you might have to serve multiple times,
but it's not fair to make you serve more than your debt.
So service not necessarily your worth in terms of how much someone
would purchase, right? Meaning the worth of your service.
Right, how much somebody would buy your six-year service for, correct. Right,
it's not like as a slave in the marketplace. Correct. Okay, אינו
נמכר כלל. eino nimkar klal. רבי אליעזר אומר אם היה גנבו כנגד
ממכרו נמכר. Rabbi Eliezer omer im haya gneivo keneged mimkaro nimkar. Now
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, talk about radically limiting the scope of a
law in the תורה. He says the only case in the תורה
where you could be sold as an עבד עברי Eved Ivri is
if the value of your six years of service is exactly equal
to what you stole. But if it's a little bit more or
a little bit less, you can't be sold. Okay, what happens then?
Then you owe the money. Okay, what happens in all other debts
you have that you can't pay? Okay, so the only time the
תורה allowed to be sold into slavery to pay a debt, right,
was the case of the גניבה. geneiva. All other debts you just
owe the money and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it's only when
it's exactly the same.
So he's saying in effect that you can never
really sell a person into slavery. Correct. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says ואם לאו אינו נמכר. ve'im lav eino nimkar. אמר רבא בהא
זכינהו רבי אליעזר לרבנן. Amar Rava beha zachinhu Rabbi Eliezer lerabbanan. רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer here showed up the rabbis, meaning the logic, the
size, you know that the גמרא gemara. seems to be happy to
limit the scope, but the logic of his position is compelling. דמאי
שנא גנב חמש מאות ושווה אלף demai shna ganav chamesh me'ot veshaveh
elef when he stole something worth five hundred and he's worth a
thousand, דאינו נמכר, de'eino nimkar, everybody agrees he's not sold, דנמכר כולו
אמר רחמנא ולא חציו. denimkar kulo amar Rachmana velo chetzyo.
Only when you're sold fully, meaning the full value of the sale
goes to the גניבה, geneiva, not when only half the value of
the sale goes to the גניבה. geneiva. הכא נמי ונמכר בגנבתו אמר
רחמנא. hacha nami venimkar bignivato amar Rachmana.
It says you're sold for the גניבה, geneiva, for the full value
of the גניבה, geneiva, ולא נמכר בחצי גנבתו, velo nimkar bechetzi gnevato,
but not when you're sold only to pay off half the גניבה.
geneiva. You have to be sold to pay off the full גניבה.
geneiva. Okay, so the same textual read and the logic should have
applied. So according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, essentially nobody will ever
be sold for their גניבה. geneiva. They can sell themselves, and the
father could sell the daughter, but they'll never be sold for their
גניבה. geneiva. Okay. Now the last line of this interesting ברייתא braita
is ומפדין אותה בעל כרחו. umafdin otah be'al korcho. You can force
the redemption of an אמה עבריה Amah Ivriya but not of an
עבד עברי. Eved Ivri Now that's a little strange because we know
the whole הלכה of an עבד עברי Eved Ivri. is that you
pay the money to the master and whether he likes it or
not, you can buy back his freedom. So the גמרא says סבר
רבא למימר בעל כרחו דאדון, savar Rava lemeimar be'al korcho de'adon, that
you can force back the redemption by an אמה עבריה Amah Ivriya
against the will of the master. אמר ליה אביי מאי ניהו. Amar
lei Abaye mai nihu. So what does it mean against his will?
דכתבינן ליה שטרא אדמיה. dechatevinan lei shtra adamei. So one way of
reading this is,
he needs the בעל כרחו
be'al korcho of עבד Eved or the other? Well, we're getting there.
Okay. But what he rejects is saying that the master is unhappy
with it, because as I said, obviously that works by an עבד
עברי Eved Ivri? as well. So what would be special about the
אמה עבריה? amah Ivriyah So maybe what's special is you don't even
have to pay the money. You could just write an IOU, right?
If it means you actually pay the money, obviously that works by
an עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. So what's working by an אמה עבריה
amah Ivriyah that's not working by an עבד עברי? Eved Ivri Well,
maybe it means without even paying cash, just writing a check, writing
an IOU. דכתבינן ליה שטרא אדמיה. dechatevinan lei shtra adamei. So אמר
ליה, Amar lei, why would you be allowed to do this? נקיט
מרגניתא בידיה. nakit marganita beyadei. He's holding onto a pearl in his
hands. He's holding onto this אמה עבריה amah Ivriyah that's worth real
money. נהבי ליה חספא? nehavi lei chaspa? And we can force him
to take a piece of pottery, a check, an IOU which is
worth nothing? I mean, obviously you don't have the money to pay
it or you wouldn't have sold your daughter to begin with, right?
So where would you get this idea that you can sell your
daughter and then just give him an IOU and get your daughter
back? Like, that's crazy. Okay, אלא, so that can't be what it
means. And it can't mean... And it can't mean cash, because that
works by עבד עברי. Eved Ivri. So what are we talking about?
אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, בעל כרחו דאב. be'al korcho de'av.
No,
you redeem her even against the objections of the father. Now what
Rashi says it means is you force the father if he has
the cash, you force him to use the cash to buy her
back, even if he doesn't want to.
Why not force him not to sell her to begin with?
Yeah, well, that's we'll see what the Gemara says. Of course, what
does that mean? He got the cash for selling her. So now
tomorrow you turn around and say, 'Oh look, you have the cash
in your bank. You just got the cash.' So presumably it means
that he has the cash and he doesn't he's not using it
like to survive with. You know, he actually has that as as
available income. Exactly who can determine that, I don't know. Okay, that's
what Rashi says and we'll see the Tosafot in a minute. Okay,
so the Gemara says, now why do you force him? משום פגם
משפחה, mishum pgam mishpacha, because having a a member of the family
sold into slavery is a mark against the entire family. So even
if the father doesn't want to, because of the concern about the,
you know, about the sort of the the name and the reputation
of the family, you force the father to buy her back.
And if the פגם pgam is also if the father has the
money and would refuse? That could also be.
That could be. So the Gemara says, אי הכי עבד עברי נמי
נכפינהו לבני משפחה. ei hachi Eved Ivri nami nachpinehu livnei mishpacha. If
a guy sells himself, why don't you force the family members to
buy him back? משום פגם משפחה? mishum pgam mishpacha? So the Gemara
says, no. הדר אזיל
ומזבין נפשיה.
hadar azil umazvin
nafshieh.
So then he'll just resell himself. That doesn't accomplish anything. Okay, and
then that'll be a good deal for him. He resells himself and
then you guys buy him back. So the Gemara says, אי הכי,
ei hachi, so the Gemara says משום פגם משפחה, mishum pgam mishpacha,
הכא נמי הדר אזיל ומזבין לה? hacha nami hadar azil umazvin lah?
So here too, you force him to buy her back, he's just
going to turn around and resell her. So the Gemara what good
is that going to do? So the Gemara's going to say, no.
קתני אינה נמכרת ושנית. katani einah nimkeret ushenit.
No, because that's why we already talked about an אמה עבריה amah
Ivriyah, cannot be resold. So because an אמה עבריה amah Ivriyah. cannot
be resold, we can force the father to buy her back and
we're not afraid that he's just going to turn around and resell
her the next day. Because he's only allowed one sale. But an
עבד עברי Eved Ivri, who can resell himself, it's not going to
do any good to force a buy back because he'll just go
ahead and sell himself again. Now Tosafot sharpens the point because Tosafot
disagrees with Rashi and says the one we're forcing to buy back
the אמה עבריה amah Ivriyah is not the father. The one we're
forcing because he was the one that needed the money, presumably that's
not the reason. The one we're forcing to buy back is the
other relatives. That for the sake of the family reputation, you sort
of like the Torah about בן דודו או דודו יגאלנו, ben dodo
o dodo yigalenu, we force the family members to buy back. And
then the question is, but then like the father, you know, is
just that's just encouraging bad behavior on the father. He sells, gets
the money, you buy back. He sells, gets the money, you buy
back. The same way the עבד עברי. Eved Ivri, I sell myself,
I get the money, you buy me back. Then I sell myself
again, I get the money, you buy me back. So the answer
is, by an עבד עברי, that's a concern. By the אמה עבריה,
amah ivriyah the father doesn't have the choice to sell her again.
So therefore we can force the בני משפחה bnei mishpacha to buy
her back. Okay, so the Gemara says ומנו רבי שמעון היא? umanu
rebbi Shimon hee? And this is Rabbi Shimon. דתניא, detanya, and now
we're going to get into this issue. Now we're going to go
deeper into this question about reselling an אמה עבריה. Okay? We before
we talked spoke talked about
an עבד עברי, that there's some cases of גניבה gneivah that he
can't be sold twice. But we didn't go into specific about the
halakha that an אמה עבריה cannot be sold twice and now we're
going to look at this. Okay, דתניא, detanya, we taught in a
baraita,
מוכר אדם את בתו לאישות ושונה. mocher adam et bito le'ishut veshoneh.
A man can sell his daughter, you gotta love the hear once
again this comparison of marrying the daughter and selling as a slave.
A man can sell מוכר אדם את בתו, mocher adam et bito,
notice by the way, can sell his daughter for marriage and do
it again. How? Because a girl who's still under age and has
not yet had נישואין, nisuin, even if she only has אירוסין, eirusin,
never leaves her father's control. So he was מקדש mekadesh his daughter,
she's still under age, it's just אירוסין, eirusin, and the guy divorces
her or dies. So now she goes back to being totally under
the father's control, he can be מקדש mekadesh her again. Okay, so
a father a man can be מקדש mekadesh his daughter multiple times
if the guy it was only אירוסין eirusin and there was divorce
or death. Okay, that you can do.
ושונה veshoneh if she's still under age. לשפחותו ושונה. leshifchuto veshoneh. Now,
against what we just said a minute ago, this baraita is saying
that he can sell his daughter as a slave and then repeat.
Now if she became free because of סימנים, simanim, obviously he cannot
repeat, she has to be a קטנה. ktanah. But let's say she
became free because of the יובל or because of six years, then
he can resell her as a slave. You can sell her as
a slave multiple times if she's still a קטנה. ktanah. לאישות אחר
שפחות. le'ishut achar shifchut.
Also if she was a slave and then it was six years,
then he can go ahead and marry her, if she is still
let's say a קטנה ktanah or נערה. na'arah. Okay, but but the
one thing he can't do according to this baraita is לא לשפחות
אחר אישות. lo leshifchut achar ishut.
After he married her and then she's free, now he can't sell
her as a slave. You could really understand that right? Because that's
like going down a level. Very degrading, first you were married as
a free woman, and now going into slavery and trying to get
married that way. But we'll see how it's learned out from the
פסוקים. psukim. So that's the only exclusion according to the תנא קמא,
tanna kamma, which is not the ברייתא braita we quoted earlier. רבי
שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, כשם שאין אדם מוכר את בתו לשפחה
אחר אישות, keshem she'ein adam mocher es bito l'shifchah achar ishus, the
same way you can't sell as a slave after a wife, כך
אין מוכר את בתו לשפחה אחר שפחה. kach ein mocher es bito
l'shifchah achar shifchah. Can't sell as a slave after being a slave,
okay. And that's the ברייתא braita we quoted earlier, and that's the
idea that it won't do any good, that's why we can force
the family to buy her back because the father won't be able
to resell her as a שפחה. shifchah. Now what is this debate
based on? בפלוגתא דהני תנאי, b'plugta d'hani tannai, it links with the
debate of these תנאים. tannaim. דתניא בברייתא, d'tanya b'braita, בבגדו בה, b'vigdo
bah, it
says לעם נכרי לא ימשל למכרה, l'am nochri lo yimshol l'mochrah,
לעם נכרי, l'am nochri,
this is after she was sold, לא ימשל למכרה, lo yimshol l'mochrah,
so he can no longer sell her
בבגדו בה, b'vigdo bah, which according to the פשט pshat of the
פסוקים psukim means like that after the father sold, well maybe one
פשט, pshat, after the father betrayed a certain trust by selling her,
he can no longer go ahead and sell her again. That's שפחה
אחר שפחה. shifchah achar shifchah. Okay, now it could also be talking
about the husband, not the father. Okay, we're going to read it
about the father. So one read is he cannot resell her after
he betrayed her by selling her once. That's שפחה אחר שפחה, shifchah
achar shifchah, okay. Now לעם נכרי l'am nochri here is just read
as any other person, that's how חז"ל chazal read it. So that
one way is reading this שפחה אחר שפחה. shifchah achar shifchah. Where
are we going to get שפחה אחר אישות, shifchah achar ishus, which
is the other way it was being read? Okay, so לעם נכרי
לא ימשל למכרה בבגדו בה, l'am nochri lo yimshol l'mochrah b'vigdo bah,
כיון שפרס טליתו עליה, keivan sheperas taliso aleha, so reading the word
בגדו bigdo as בגד, beged, once you spread your cloak over her,
meaning which is marriage, like בפרשת רות, b'parashas Rus, שוב אין רשאי
למכרה, shuv ein rashai l'mochrah, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva.
You can't sell her after marriage. So בגדו bigdo reading בגד, beged,
it can't be שפחה אחר אישות. shifchah achar ishus. That was the
position of the תנא קמא. tanna kamma.
Now we read it as בוגד. boged.
That's the next read. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, בבגדו בה,
b'vigdo bah, כיון שבגד בה, keivan shebagad bah, betrayed her by selling
her as a slave, שוב אינו רשאי למכרה. shuv eino rashai l'mochrah.
So that's שפחה אחר שפחה. shifchah achar shifchah. So it's either שפחה
אחר אישות shifchah achar ishus if it's בגד beged or שפחה אחר
שפחה shifchah achar shifchah if it's בגידה. begidah. Okay, now במאי קמיפלגי,
bemai kamiflagi,
what's that debate based on? רבי אליעזר סבר יש אם למסורת. Rabbi
Eliezer savar yeish em l'masores. Now there's a whole question how to
read this גמרא. רבי עקיבא סבר יש אם למקרא. Rabbi Akiva savar
yeish em l'mikra. So the way רש"י Rashi reads it is מקרא
mikra means the way it's read. So בבגדו, b'vigdo, does the word
בבגדו, b'vigdo, does that mean בגידה begidah or בגד? beged? רש"י Rashi
claims that the word בבגדו, b'vigdo, like if you think about it,
בבגדו b'vigdo means
his בגד. beged. בבגדו. b'vigdo. If it were to mean betrayal it
would be בבגדו, b'vogdo, רש"י Rashi says. בבגדו. b'vogdo. Okay, so בבגדו,
b'bigdo, that's read as בבגדו, b'bigdo, but it's not written as בבגדו
b'bigdo because to be written as בבגדו b'bigdo you'd have to have
a
י, yud, okay. So רבי
אליעזר סבר יש אם למסורת, Rabbi Eliezer savar yeish em l'masores, the
way it's written and it's written בגדו, bagdo, so that's after rebellion
it's שפחה אחר שפחה. shifchah achar shifchah. רבי עקיבא סבר יש אם
למקרא. Rabbi Akiva savar yeish em l'mikra. בבגדו b'bigdo is read as
בגד, beged, it's שפחה אחר אישות. shifchah achar ishus. So that's one
or the other. Now if you remember in the ברייתא, braita, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon said he can't sell her as a שפחה shifchah
either after שפחה shifchah or after אישות, ishus, right? Once there was
one sale, שפחה shifchah or אישות, ishus, it cannot be followed with
שפחה shifchah after. So רבי שמעון סבר יש אם למקרא ולמסורת. Rabbi
Shimon savar yeish em l'mikra v'gam l'masores. He reads it both ways,
whether it's שפחה אחר שפחה shifchah achar shifchah or שפחה אחר אישות,
shifchah achar ishus, either way cannot be done. For according to him
the only thing that could be done is אישות אחר אישות, ishus
achar ishus, okay. I guess אישות אחר שפחה ishus achar shifchah could
be done. But שפחה shifchah can never be done after there was
one type of sale. Okay, so that's the idea that an אמה
עבריה is not נמכרת ושונה nimkeres v'shonah and also why we can
compel the family to buy her back, if that's true, because then
we're not afraid he's just going to go ahead and resell her.